<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Public Economics</title>
    <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/index.html</link>
    <description>Recent content on Public Economics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>nments</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/assignments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/assignments/</guid>
      <description>Grade Calculator  Use this tool to calculate your final course grade and predict what grades you would need on remaining assignments to obtain a desired course grade.
Country Profile Each of you will write a short profile of a different developing country and give a short presentation to the class. The countries that may be chosen will be restricted to developing economies in Latin America, Asia, Africa, and Eastern Europe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reference</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reference/</guid>
      <description>Contents  Tips for Success   Look here over the course of the semester for resources, links, and tips on how to succeed in the course, how to write well, and other things of interest related to economic development.
Tips for Success Take notes. On paper. Really. Studies show that using pen and paper trump taking notes on a device. The main reason is because you cannot possibly write down everything I am saying by hand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schedule</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/schedule/</guid>
      <description>This page contains all of the following resources for each class meeting:
  Readings include textbook chapters and occasional journal articles  Assignments are due by the beginning of class unless otherwise stated  Class materials contain extra explanations, math/statistical properties &amp;amp; proofs, and other helpful resourcesThese “online appendices” keep the slides nice and de-cluttered!
  Slides are “Xaringan” presentations in html that can be opened in any browserFile &amp;gt; Print &amp;gt; Save as PDF if you wish to download them</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>Download as PDF Last Updated: January 9, 2020   “What’s so great about democracy other than it’s democratic?” – Gordon Tullock
  “Democracy is the worst form of government, except for all the others that have been tried from time to time.” – Winston Churchill
 The Public Sector&amp;#8853;Instructor
Dr. Ryan Safner
 118 Rosenstock
safner@hood.edu
@ryansafner
 Office hours: TuTh 3:15–5:00PM
Course
 MW</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>