<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Readings on Economics of Development</title>
    <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Readings on Economics of Development</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>10. The Natural State and the Violence Trap - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/10-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/10-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  Chapter 1 in North, Wallis, Webb, Weingast (2013) In the Shadow of Violence: Politics, Economics, and the Problems of Development  Econtalk (2006): “Bruce Bueno de Mesquita on the Political Economy of Power”  This chapter (from an edited volume of essays) outlines the theory of what North, Wallis, and Weingast call “limited-access orders” (LAOs) in contrast to “open access orders.” Their theory is fully spelled out in the excellent book Violence and Social Orders (2009), where they alternatively call limited access orders “natural states.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11. The Origins of Liberal Democracy in Western Europe - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/11-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/11-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  Chapters 4, 7 in Daron Acemoglu and James A RobinsonWhy Nations Fail: The Origins of Power, Prosperity, and Poverty (New York: Crown Business, 2008).
  Recommended   Levy and Pert, “How the Dismal Science Got its Name”  The History of Europe: Every Year  Primary Sources   North and Weingast (1989), “Constitutions and Commitment: The Evolution of Institutional Governing Public Choice in Seventeenth-Century England”  Weingast (2017), “Adam Smith’s Theory of Violence and the Political-Economics of Development”  Ko, Koyama, and Sng (2017), “Unified China and Divided Europe”  Koyama and Johnson (2016), “States and Economic Growth: Capacity and Constraints”  Milgrom, North, and Weingast (1990), “The Role of Institutions in the Revival of Trade: The Law Merchant, Private Judges, and the Champaigne Fairs”  Grief (1989), “Reputation and Coalitions in Medieval Trade: the Case of the Maghribi Traders”  Grief, Milgrom, and Weingast (1994), “Coordination, Commitment, and Enforcement: The Case of the Merchant Guild”  Ogilvie (2014), “The Economics of Guilds”  Benson (1989), “The Spontaneous Evolution of Commercial Law” Read the quotes by classical economists (Smith, Hume, Bastiat) on mercantilism, starting on slide 153  Questions to Read For:  Why did the Industrial Revolution occur England in the 1800s?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12. Russia and the Post-Communist Transition - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/12-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/12-reading/</guid>
      <description>We wrap up with a look at the economic histories of Russia, the Soviet Union, and the transition from Communism in former Soviet countries. Certainly this is a big topic that would require more time and readings to do it justice, but I have found a few that will provide a good summary. We want to focus on two major questions:
How did the economy actually work under Soviet Socialism?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2. Measuring Development - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/02-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/02-reading/</guid>
      <description>Updated Wednesday, September 4, 2019
Recommended Readings:   Sen (1988), “The Concept of Development”  Boettke and Subrick (2003), “Rule of Law, Development, and Human Capabilities”  TED Talk: Hans Rosling on the Best Stats You’ve Ever Seen  BBC: Hans Rosling’s 200 Countries, 200 Years, 4 Minutes  TED Talk: Hans Rosling on the Magic Washing Machine  We will not have a discussion on these readings for this lesson.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3. Can We Plan an Economy? - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/03-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/03-reading/</guid>
      <description>This will be the first major reading and discussion that we will have this semester. On Monday I will explain how we will hold discussions, as well as provide more context for you to interpret the readings.
Required Readings:   Mises (1920), “Economic Calculation in the Socialist Commonwealth”  Recommended Readings: I will often try to find some “readings” that are also short, and/or are in other media formats (like videos or podcasts).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4. The Microeconomics of Development - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/04-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/04-reading/</guid>
      <description>This lesson will have no discussion, I will lecture for 2 periods, and then we will transition to the next lesson, which will end in a discussion.
Recommended Readings:   Smith (1776), Wealth of Nations, Book I, Chs. 1-3  Hayek (1945), “The Use of Knowledge in Society”  Bauer (2000), “From Subsistence to Exchange”  TED Talk: Thomas Thwaites: How I Built a Toaster From Scratch&#34;  YouTube: How to Make a $1500 Sandwich in Only 6 Months&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5. The Macroeconomics of Development - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/05-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/05-reading/</guid>
      <description>I will lecture for 1.5-3 periods, and then we will have a discussion on either Monday Sept 30.
Required Readings:  Chapter 3 in William EasterlyThe Elusive Quest for Growth: Economists Adventures and Misadventures in the Tropics (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2002).
  Recommended Readings:  Marginal Revolution University Videos on Growth, Capital Accumulation, and the Economics of Ideas  Nordhaus (2000), “Do Real-Output and Real-Wage Measures Capture Reality?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6. Foreign Aid - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/06-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/06-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  Chapters 2,6 in William EasterlyThe Elusive Quest for Growth: Economists Adventures and Misadventures in the Tropics (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2002).
  Recommended Readings   Sachs (2014), “The Case for Aid,” Foreign Policy  Easterly (2015), “The Father of Millions” Wall Street Journal  Primary Sources   Burnside and Dollar (2000), “Aid, Policies, and Growth”  Easterly et. al (2003), “New Data, New Doubts: Comment on Burnside and Dollar”  Ovaska (2003), “The Failure of Development Aid”  Rodrik (2006), “Goodbye Washington Consensus, Hello Washington Confusion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7. Geography and Uncontrollable Factors - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/07-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/07-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  Chapter 2 in Daron Acemoglu and James A RobinsonWhy Nations Fail: The Origins of Power, Prosperity, and Poverty (New York: Crown Business, 2008).
  Sachs, Mellinger, and Gallup (2001), “The Geography of Poverty”  Acemoglu and Robinson’s work is famous for arguing that institutions are the fundamental cause of differences in income and growth around the world. This chapter argues that other theories–geography, culture, and ignorance–are insufficient to explain the differences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8. Political Economy - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/08-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/08-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  Chapter 3 in Daron Acemoglu and James A RobinsonWhy Nations Fail: The Origins of Power, Prosperity, and Poverty (New York: Crown Business, 2008).
  Chapter 3 outlines the central thesis of the book: that differences in income per capita around the world today, and the trajectories of economic development are determined by political and economic institutions. AJRThe common nickname for “Acemoglu, Johnson, and Robinson”, who frequently collaborate on these issues (see the primary sources below).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9. The Pre-Modern Malthusian World - Readings</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/09-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/09-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Readings:  Chapter 1 in Scott (1999) Seeing Like a State  Olson (1993), “Dictatorship, Democracy, and Development”  James Scott is a political scientist and anthropologist who specializes in agrarian and non-State societies. This is one of several provocative books, but the main contribution of this particular book (and chapter) is to highlight the lack of state capacity and its implications. It will really give you a detailed description of how States require “legibility” to command and control resources, and just how illegible societies really are, particularly before the rise of powerful States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Is Development?</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/01-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/01-reading/</guid>
      <description> Required     </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>