<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Readings on Public Economics</title>
    <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Readings on Public Economics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>1.2. Externalities and Bargaining - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.2-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.2-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Reading:   Coase (1960), “The Problem of Social Cost”  Tips and Questions to Read for: This is an extremely famous paperIt is one of the most cited papers in Economics of the 20th Century.
, which almost single-handedly launched the discipline of Law and EconomicsI plan to finally teach a course in this in Spring 2021!
, one of the two papers that won Coase the 1991 Economics Nobel Prize.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.3. Property Rights - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.3-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.3-reading/</guid>
      <description> Required Reading:   Demsetz (1967), “Toward a Theory of Property Rights”  Tips and Questions to Read for:  What are the benefits and costs of property rights?
 Why don’t we make everything property? Why might we leave some things un-“propertized”?
 What is the relationship between property rights and externalities?
 How is this article related to Coase’s article?
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.4. Collective Action - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.4-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.4-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Reading:   Olson (1982), The Rise and Decline of Nations, Chapter 2, “The Logic”  Sorry about the formatting!
Tips and Questions to Read for:  What are the similarities/differences between individual interests and group interests (for groups to which individuals belong)?
 What does Olson say is Marx’s shortcoming of his approach to groups (economic classes)?
 What are the economic differences between large groups and small groups, in terms of individual incentives?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.5. Efficiency and Justice - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.5-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/1.5-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Reading:   Sandel, 2009, “Justice” Lectures 5 (Free to Choose) and 14 (A Deal is a Deal)  These are lectures from Michael Sandel’s Justice class at Harvard, one of the most popular courses. Due to the way these videos are cut, I encourage (but don’t require) you to watch part of the lecture immediately following each lecture mentioned above (e.g. lectures 6 and 15) as it continues the relevant discussions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.1. Politics as Constraints - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/2.1-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/2.1-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Reading:   Hobbes (1651), Selections from The Leviathan  Machiavelli (1532), Selections from The Price  This class kicks off our look at Constitutional Political Economy, and we will examine this topic at several levels:
First, if we are to chose as a group at any level (whether a national government, a neighborhood association, or a book club), how do we constitute and decide how to decide as a group?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.2. Beyond the Reach of Majorities - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/2.2-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/2.2-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Reading:   Locke (1689), Selections from The Second Treatise on Government  Madison (1787-1788), Federalist 10 and 51  Last class was about government placing constraints on citizens, and it being in everyone’s interest to accept these. This class is about citizens placing constraints on government. We might summarize this dual dilemma by paraphrasing Madison’s Federalist 51:
 “In framing a government which is to be administered by men over men, the great difficulty lies in this: you must first enable the government to control the governed; and in the next place oblige it to control itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.3. The Optimal Decision Rule - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/2.3-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/2.3-reading/</guid>
      <description>Required Reading:   Buchanan and Tullock (1962), The Calculus of Consent, Chs. 3,5,6Again, you can buy several versions of this book, or here is the link to free PDF
  After we’ve digested some political philosophy (with a dose of game theory), it’s time for a more “rigorous” model of choosing as a group. How should we decide how to decide?
We read the key chapters of Buchanan and Tullock’s classic 1962 Calculus of Consent, which (mostly) launched the field of public choice as the economic analysis of politics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.1. Voting I: Preference Aggregation &amp; Cycling - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.1-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.1-reading/</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, February 19, 2020
Required Reading:   Holcombe (2016), Advanced Introduction to Public Choice, Chs. 2,3,5  We will not have a discussion today, you do not need to email questions. This material will be a bit more dense and technical, and I will lecture for the full period. However, doing the reading will also be very helpful, even though you will not be graded on it in any way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.2. Voting II: Ignorance &amp; Irrationality - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.2-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.2-reading/</guid>
      <description>Monday, February 24, 2020
Required Reading:   Caplan (2007), “The Myth of the Rational Voter”  For today, after I finish up what’s left of my lecture from last Wednesday on Voting I, we will discuss the (in)famous concept of rational ignorance, as well as rational irrationality. Your reading for today is on the latter, since it is more debatable, and since I can explain the former to you very quickly in class (and give a demonstration).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.3. Voting III: Democracy Squared? - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.3-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.3-reading/</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, February 26, 2020
Required Reading:   Posner, Eric A, and E Glen Weyl (2017), Radical Markets, Ch. 2: “Radical Democracy”  Today we discuss one of the more interesting (and radical) proposals put forth to reform politics in a fundamental (and economic) way: to dispense with “one person one vote,” allowing people to express the intensity of their preferences with (essentially) “multiple votes” that they can “buy” at an increasing cost (allowing them to make tradeoffs).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.4. Special Interest Groups - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.4-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.4-reading/</guid>
      <description>Monday, March 2, 2020
Required Reading:   Stigler, George J, 1971, “The Theory of Economic Regulation,” The Bell Journal of Economics and Management Science 2(1): 3-21  Yandle, Bruce, 1983, “Bootleggers and Baptists: The Education of a Regulatory Economist,” Regulation 7(3): 12-16  Today we briefly discuss the logic of interest groups, and moreso about the effects they have on public policy and regulation. Your readings focus on both the economic outcomes of regulation and a theory of how and why regulation favors particular groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.5. Legislators - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.5-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.5-reading/</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, March 4, 2020
Required Reading:  [ Weingast, Barry R and William J Marshall, 1988, “The Industrial Organization of Congress; or, Why Legislatures, Like Firms, Are Not Organized as Markets” Journal of Political Economy 96(1): 132-163  We now look at politicians as legislators in a representative democracy: agents elected by voters and interest groups within a district to serve their interests by enacting laws in a larger legislature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.6. Bureaucracy - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.6-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.6-reading/</guid>
      <description>Monday, March 23, 2020
Online Quarantine Lecture 1
Readings:   Holcombe (2016), Advanced Introduction to Public Choice, Ch. 9 “Bureaucracy”  Mises, Ludwig von (1949), Human Action: A Treatise on Economics, Ch. XV.10, “Promoters, Managers, Technicians, and Bureaucrats” (Skim)  We now look at those individuals and organizations that actually implement the laws, collectively known as “the bureaucracy,” sometimes called “the fourth branch of government.” These are both executive-branch departments (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.7. The Rise of the Administrative State - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.7-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.7-reading/</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, March 25, 2020
Readings:   Cooper, Charles J, 2015, “Confronting the Administrative State,” National Affairs
  Optional: Wilson, Woodrow, 1887, “The Study of Administration,” Political Science Quarterly
  We continue looking at bureaucracy and the role of independent agencies and regulatory commissions, and examine their tension with democracy and, some may argue, the constitution. Naturally, this conversation begins to have an ideological tinge to it, so we look at both the progressive and conservative takes on “the administrative state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.8. Federalism - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.8-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.8-reading/</guid>
      <description>Monday, March 29, 2020
We will wrap up our “structural” look at the major political groups and institutions in American-style democracy with a look at federalism - the multiplicity of governments (federal, state, and local) each with authority over different domains of American life.
Weingast (1995) is a pretty famous paper in political economy; he uses a fairly straightforward application of the game theory of credible commitment problems to explain how a federalist system such as the United States can successfully constrain government from abusing its power.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3.9. Exit, Voice, and Loyalty - Readings</title>
      <link>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.9-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://publicS20.classes.ryansafner.com/reading/3.9-reading/</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, April 1, 2020
One of the benefits of federalism we saw from last class is the Tiebout competition that allows citizens to “vote with their feet,” which constrains governmental units from abusing their power or financial responsibilities. This class, we extend this idea in a much broader way, using a very famous frameowrk from a book by Albert HirschmanThe most interesting 20th Century economist you’ve never heard of.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>