<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Assignments on Economics of Development</title>
    <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Assignments on Economics of Development</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Country Profile Assignment</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/country-profile/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/country-profile/</guid>
      <description>Due last day of class: Monday December 9  Overview Each of you will write a short profile of a different developing country and give a short presentation to the class. The countries that may be chosen will be restricted to developing economies in Latin America, Asia, Africa, and Eastern Europe. Students born outside of the U.S. may not choose the country of their birth. The purpose of this assignment is to “get you out of your comfort zone” and see the world from the perspective of a culture and an economy radically different than the one(s) you are familiar with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final Exam</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/final-exam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/final-exam/</guid>
      <description>Due 8:00 PM Friday, December 13 by email  Instructions Choose two questions from section 1 and two questions from section 2 (4 in total) to answer. Questions draw from course lectures, discussions, and readings. Your answers, given the time and resources at your disposal, should be complete yet concise (e.g. 2-3 well-reasoned paragraphs).
You may discuss the questions, but you must write your own responses and turn in your own work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Paper 1</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/01-short-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/01-short-paper/</guid>
      <description>Due Wednesday, October 30   “How can I know what I think until I see what I say?” — E. M. Forster on Writing
 Overview Your task is to write a short paper on a theme that we have discussed or addressed in this course thus far – whether in my lectures, our discussions, or your reading. This assignment has several purposes. First, it is my way of gauging whether you understand the material and are attempting to grapple with the challenges it brings to understanding economics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Paper 2</title>
      <link>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/02-short-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devf19.classes.ryansafner.com/assignment/02-short-paper/</guid>
      <description>Due 8:00 PM Friday, December 6 by email  Overview This assignment is the same as short paper 1. Please see that assignment’s page for reminders about structure and grading.
Potential Topic Prompts I would prefer for you to choose a topic from lesson 8 onwards. Again, you are free to choose your own topic, and might wish to write about something similar to your first short paper or something based on some of the comments and feedback I gave you.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>